The lecture Wang Zhe mentioned,
王哲说的讲座
are you signing up or not?
你报不报啊
I don't know yet.
不知道啊
Ms. Xue
你妈
already called your Mom in for a talk.
都被薛老师叫家长了
You didn't get good results
这两次你摸底考试
in the past two mock exams.
成绩都不理想
Why not attend the lecture?
还不去听听呢
Yeah, if my mom finds out,
对啊 我妈知道了
I'm probably done.
那估计悬了
Sign up, and let's go together.
报吧 咱俩一起
At least we'd have company.
还能有个伴
Liu Siming's Mom
刘思明他妈
already signed him up.
都给他报名了
I saw it in
我在我妈
my mom's parents' chat group.
家长群里看见的
I can only hope
我现在就只能祈祷
my mom's too busy with work
我妈工作忙点
to check the chat messages.
家长群她没有看到吧
As long as she doesn't push it,
只要我妈不坚持
my dad won't force me
我爸就一定不会
to sign up.
给我报名的
My dad is
我爸呢
a bit different from other parents.
跟别人不太一样
He says studying is like
他说学习是一场
competing with oneself.
自己跟自己的较量
So no need to stress
不要在乎
over short-term wins and losses.
一城一池的得失
Stop showing off.
凡尔赛
I'm not going.
我不去
I'm joining the performance.
我就要去参加演出
Your mom was called to school.
你妈妈都被叫家长了
With your grades right now,
就你现在这个成绩
you have to push yourself
我们要自己给自己
and put in
加点量
some extra effort.
努努劲了
Didn't you say studying is like a marathon?
你不是说学习是长跑吗
Don't sweat
不要在乎
the small stuff.
一城一池的得失
I meant that strategically.
我说的是战略上的
I mean,
我的意思
one should have
人要有一个长远的
a long-term goal.
一个目标
And right now, your goal
那眼下你的目标
is the high-school entrance exam,
那就是中考
right?
是不是
There are only six months left.
就剩下半年多了
You need to tackle those hurdles
我们要一城一池地
bit by bit.
往下攻啊
I'll skip this one.
那我这次不去
But I'll go next time, okay?
我下次去行了吧
Are you kidding me?
你开什么玩笑啊
This is for your own good.
我是为了你好
And besides,
再说了
you don't take piano lessons now.
你这钢琴课是不都停了
Why bother with the performance?
你参加什么汇报演出
What's the point?
有什么意义呢
I'm doing this for you!
都是为了你好
No, that's not true.
什么为了我好呀
You're doing it for yourself!
都是为了你自己
Ever since mom got pregnant,
自从我妈怀孕之后
you haven't cared about
家里什么事情
anything at home.
你都不操心
When the new baby comes,
以后有了二胎
you'll probably forget all about me.
估计连我是谁你都忘了
I don't care?
我不操心啊
I've been helping with
我给你
your homework...
你的 你的功课
Enough, enough.
行了 行了
Just stop arguing!
行了 别吵了
You think I don't care?
我还不操心
Look,
这个
Yunjie,
云阶
there's still time before
不是还有一段时间
the entrance exam.
才中考呢吗
I've got an idea.
我想了一个主意
How about I pull some strings
要不然我托托关系
and get Yunjie into
把云阶
the top school in our county?
送到咱们县一中去上学
What do you think?
怎么样
Good.
好
Great idea!
好主意
It's decided then.
就这么定了
Dad!
爸
What?
你爸什么爸
Your dad
你爸
went to that school years ago.
就是从县一中读出来的
Ask him.
你问问你爸
It's a strict school,
人家管得可严了
and you have to study hard there.
头悬梁 锥刺股
Even your cousin Huahua
你华华哥哥
got into a university in Beijing
就是从县中考上的北京
from there.
上的大学
Got it?
懂不啦
I'm not going!
我不去
Hey,
姐
do you have something cooking on the stove?
你是不火上做着东西呢
I smell something burning.
怎么一股糊味啊
Oh no, I forgot!
忘了
Please, be good, okay?
你 你听话 听话啊
Auntie got too busy and forgot.
姑姑都忙蒙了
I don't care.
我不管
I'm not going.
我就是不去
I want to be in the performance!
我要去参加演出
So?
怎么样
I said what I needed to.
我该说的都说了吧
Well, you blew it.
那你搞砸了呀
Fine, let's see if you can do better.
好啊 你去搞个不砸的
I won't give up easily.
我还就不信了
Let's see what you've got.
看你本事了
I told you before,
就跟你说过
you can't raise a kid like that.
孩子不能这么教育
But you...
你这
It's important to find the right approach.
方式 方法很重要
But you insist on doing it your way.
非得自己那一套
You just don't get it.
你也不懂
Just leave it to me.
交给我
And I've done
我这 教育得挺好的
a great job so far.
管得挺好的
You just have to...
非得弄得
Now she's upset.
你看生气了吧 现在
She might even
那钢琴
smash the piano.
都能给你砸了一会儿
That's beautiful.
真好听
You know,
你知道吗
every day when I leave for work,
每天妈上班的时候
the moment I step out that door,
只要一出这个门
I feel like
就觉得好像
I'm going into battle.
要提枪上战场
But when I step through this door,
但是我一进这个门
I think to myself,
我就想
this home is just perfect.
这个家特别好
I've got such a
有我一个
wonderful daughter.
特别优秀的女儿
And my heart
妈妈
softens right up.
就内心一片柔软
I feel my heart
被幸福和这个
is wrapped in love
满足
and contentment.
充斥着内心
That's vivid.
你形容得真好
I should jot this down.
我得拿个小本本记上
I might use it for my next essay.
下次写作文能用上呢
Don't change the subject, okay?
别打岔行吗
I'm, after all,
你妈好歹也是
a journalism graduate.
新闻系毕业的
OK?
好吧
I know how to be sentimental.
煽情还是可以的
You're good at liberal arts.
你文科成绩好
You get that from me.
不就是随了我吗
Dad always says,
我爸还说
I'm not good at science,
我理科成绩不好
and that's your fault too.
也是随了你呢
I'd say his genes
那我觉得是他理科基因
just couldn't beat mine.
没有战胜我的文科基因
Mom, you
妈 你真是
never lose an argument.
吵架 永远都不会输
Not always.
也不一定
Sometimes
有时候
when I can't find the right words,
组织不好语言的时候
I'll lose.
也影响发挥
When I think about it later,
复盘的时候就想拍大腿
I regret not saying
我当时怎么
those few lines.
没说那几句呢
Right?
是吧
Exactly!
对
That's the feeling!
就是这种感觉
Spot on.
精辟
It's all a strategy.
套路
Mom,
妈
what did the teacher talk to you about?
老师找你 说什么了呀
Oh, nothing much.
也没什么
She just showed me
就给我看了
some of your test papers.
几张你的卷子
Your teacher also said,
你们老师也说了
you've had a lot of new material
是因为前段时间呢
to learn lately.
学习新知识 有点多
So you haven't had
然后就
much time to review.
不就没时间复习吗
Let's take some time
那咱就花点时间
to go over the new stuff, okay?
巩固一下呗
Just consolidate what you've learned,
那巩固巩固
and your grades will go up.
这成绩不就上来了吗
Right?
对吧
But I've been
可我这段时间
so exhausted lately.
真的很累了
That's common.
谁不累呀
I'm stressed too.
妈妈压力也很大的
You know I'm pregnant
你知道妈现在上班
and still working.
怀着二胎
I have to be extra careful at the office.
那是谨小慎微啊
I can't afford any mistakes.
不敢出一点错
Plus, I'm training new hires.
然后还得带新人
I've also got to assign all the work
还得安排产假的时候
before taking my maternity leave.
那些工作
If I don't
要不然你说
plan everything well,
安排不好的话
when I come back from leave,
回头产假休完了
I might not have a job waiting for me.
工作都没了
Is it really that serious?
这么严重啊
What do you think?
你以为呢
Let me tell you,
我告诉你
the workplace is brutal.
职场很残酷的
Doing a good job doesn't always guarantee promotions or raises.
干得好不一定升职加薪
But if you screw up,
干不好
and you're definitely getting the boot.
肯定卷铺盖卷儿走人
Playing the pity card?
卖惨
Getting into high school isn't easy either.
我们考高中也不容易啊
So,
所以啊
let's work hard together,
咱俩一块努力呗
shall we?
对不对
We can set a schedule
咱们定一个时间表
and stick to it.
然后呢 按部就班
You focus on studying for exams,
你努力考中考
and I'll focus on having this baby.
妈努力生二胎
It's just six months,
不就半年吗
we'll get through it.
一扛 就过去了
Mom,
妈
I feel like
我感觉
Dad,
爸爸他
he doesn't like me as much anymore.
好像没那么喜欢我了
How could that be?
这怎么可能
My sweet girl,
我的儿啊
that's impossible.
不能的
Honestly,
其实
I haven't fully come to terms
你们要生二胎这件事情
with you having another baby.
我也没有完全消化得了
But recently,
只是前段时间
Grandpa has been sick,
外公生病
Auntie had an early delivery,
小姨早产
and you need bed rest,
你还要保胎
I think I need to be more grown-up about it.
我觉得我不能不懂事
You've been through so much.
可怜了
My poor baby.
我的孩儿
Honey.
她爸
I'm here.
在呢
Hurry up. Say something.
你赶紧的 表个态
Your daughter even thinks
你闺女说
you don't love her anymore.
你都不喜欢她了
What? That's not true!
怎 怎么可能呢
How could I not love you?
我怎么可能不喜欢你呢
You're my daughter, Yunjie.
你是我女儿哎 云阶
I still remember it like yesterday
爸爸到现在还记得
the first time I held you in my arms.
第一次抱你的感觉
When you were just born,
你刚出生那会儿
the nurse handed you to me
护士把你递给我
and told me to hold you a bit higher.
让我把手臂抬高一点
Your tiny head
你的小脑袋
was snuggled right up against me.
就这样紧紧地贴着我
I was so tense that
我当时整个人
my upper body was frozen.
上半身都僵在那儿
I couldn't even move.
动都不敢动
I was terrified that if I did,
我怕我一动
I might hurt you.
把你弄坏了
But I was so happy.
但是我好开心啊
It was the first time
这是我
I'd ever felt such pure joy.
第一次有这样的幸福感
And then the first time
还有后来我第一次
I took you to kindergarten.
送你上幼儿园
The first day of elementary school.
第一次送你上小学
The first day of middle school.
第一次送你上初中
All those firsts,
就这些第一次
no one else could give me that.
别的孩子给不了我
Yunjie,
那个 云阶
this whole second child thing
这个生二胎这个事情
it's not as heavy as you think.
没有你想得那么沉重的
Do you know what your teacher
你知道你老师
said about this?
是怎么说的吗
She said,
她说
it's like playing a game.
打游戏
You're like the main account.
你就是大号
The second child is like an alt account.
这是小号
Even if we're leveling up the alt,
就算现在在养小号
we still
但是大号
keep the main account logged in.
也要一直登录 上着的
What kind of comparison that?
这什么比喻呀
Well, it might sound odd, but it's true.
话 话糙理不糙嘛
Yeah.
是
You're a teenager now.
你现在 是青春期
We know
我们都知道
you have the urge to push boundaries
有着一些超越世界
and to break free.
超越自我的力量
But we don't
但是我们不希望
want you to
你把这种力量啊
push us away.
放在和父母的对立面上
I'm not trying to oppose you.
我不是要跟你们对立
And it's not that I don't want to attend the lecture.
也不是不想去听讲座
I just want to
我就是想
end my piano journey
想给我的学琴生涯
on a high note.
画上一个圆满的句号
Didn't you always say
你们不是说过吗
to finish what you start?
要有始有终
To have a sense of closure?
仪式感
Yeah, that's it.
对 仪式感
Okay.
好
Go ahead.
可以
You've got my support.
爸支持
Awesome!
好耶
Count me in.
带我一个呗
Come on!
来来来
Stand up, both of you.
你们站起来 站起来
Alright.
好
I can't squat down.
蹲不下
Where is your sister?
姐去哪儿了
She went to buy soy sauce.
打酱油去了
What's she cooking in the pot?
她锅里做的什么呀
Yeah, it smells so strong.
对啊 这么大味
What, what is this?
这什么呀 这是
What is she cooking?
这都弄的什么
Why so many ingredients?
这么多
Is my lamb kidney soup ready?
我的羊肾汤好了吧
Jing, what on earth did you make?
大姐 你这炖的什么呀
Eucommia Lamb Kidney Soup. Drink when it's still warm.
杜仲羊肾汤 得趁热喝
What?
什么羊肾
Just lamb kidneys.
就羊腰子
No wonder.
难怪了
That smell... it's quite unpleasant.
这味道 就很不愉悦
Can't you smell it?
你知道吗
What a waste.
可惜了
Well, you can drink it.
你喝吧
Why should I?
我干吗喝呀
I'm not the one on bed rest.
我又不安胎
These herbs are expensive.
这药材很贵的
Besides,
再说啊
men need to take care of their health too,
男人到了中年以后啊
especially in middle ages.
也得要补
I don't need it. I'm perfectly healthy.
不需要啊 我好得很
Nonsense.
好什么好得很 你
It's good for your health.
你 一定要补
You know?
知道吧
This...
这个
These two
这俩啊
know nothing about nourishing food.
一对不懂养生
But yeah, that smell is pretty strong.
味是大了点
Take the baby away, take her away!
抱走 抱走
I'm not breastfeeding. I don't have milk.
我不喂奶 没有奶
Mrs. Jia, look,
宝妈
isn't our Little Watermelon adorable?
看看我们漂亮的小西瓜
Get out.
出去
Hurry, out!
快点出去
Leave me alone!
出去 出去
Quick, quick, out.
快快快 出去
She's asleep now.
睡着了啊 宝宝
So lovely.
真好看啊
How pretty.
好看
Honey, honey.
媳妇 媳妇
You, get out too.
你也出去
You're ugly too.
你也丑
Of course I'm ugly, I know. But sweetie,
我当然丑 我知道 媳妇
our Little Watermelon isn't.
咱家小西瓜不丑
She's a real beauty, you know?
大美女 你知道吗
Don't touch me.
别碰我
What an ugly smile.
笑得真丑
What's up?
干吗
Honey,
媳妇
do you know
你知道
what you remind me of
我现在看你这个样子
right now?
我想起什么了吗
A queen from Journey to the West.
西游记里面一个皇后
Which one?
什么皇后
Is she beautiful?
好看吗
She is stunning.
国色天香
Prettier than me?
比我还好看
Of course not.
当然没你漂亮
You remind me of
我看你
someone from that novel too.
也像西游记里的一个人
Who?
谁呀
Pigsy.
二师兄
Honey,
老婆
I'm not even as good as him.
我还不如二师兄呢
He can wield
那人家二师兄猪八戒
that nine-toothed rake.
一个大耙子抡来抡去
I'm nothing compared to him.
我差远了
My ugliness only makes
我的丑就是为了衬托
your beauty shine brighter.
你国色天香
Your grace
花容月貌
and charm
闭月羞花
are unparalleled.
沉鱼落雁
You've been reading a lot lately, huh?
你最近看了不少书嘛
Absolutely, my love.
那是啊 媳妇
I've been reading to learn
我读书是有原因的
how to praise
我就是从字里行间
my beautiful wife.
为了赞美我老婆的美
I'm thirsty.
我渴了
I want some water.
要喝水
I'm on it.
来了
Your wish is my command!
我的媳妇要喝水
Clank, clank, clank!
铿 铿 铿
Jing,
姐
I'm heading out.
我走了啊
It's so late,
这么晚了
aren't you going to work?
你怎么还没去上班啊
Not to the office. I've got to meet someone.
不去公司 我约了人
Hold on a second.
等一下
Pick a pair.
选一双
Me?
我吗
Yeah.
对呀
Now that you're pregnant,
你现在怀孕了
you've got to stay warm,
要特别注意保暖
especially your feet.
尤其这个三阴交
But I'm pregnant,
我现在怀孕了
my body's burning with energy.
火力壮得很
And it's already so hot outside.
而且天都这么热了
Wearing these will make me sweat.
穿这个容易出汗哪
Well,
你看
that's where you're mistaken.
这就是你不懂了吧
In Traditional Chinese Medicine,
在我们中医上讲
we say it's external heat but internal deficiency.
就是外热内虚
In Western medicine,
西医上讲
pregnancy hormones
就是因为孕激素
are making your joints
导致全身的骨头缝
loosen up,
全开了
leaving you vulnerable
这个寒风啊 就会
to the cold wind.
钻遍你的全身哪
The worst part is,
它最缺德的
it'll affect you for the rest of your life.
就是只进不出
When you're older,
到老了
you'll suffer
完啦
arthritis,
关节炎哪
sore legs, and other diseases.
老寒腿呀 都来
Fine, fine,
姐 姐
I'll wear them.
那 我穿
Is that okay?
穿 好吧
Put them on.
穿上
You must keep
这个三阴交啊
your feet warm.
一定要保护好
Give me.
来
Good. That's better.
对 这就对了
Alright, I'm off now.
那我走了
With you around,
有我姐在
I don't have to worry about anything.
我啥都不用管了
Take care.
你 你路上注意安全啊
Will do.
好嘞
Alright, I'm heading out.
那我走了啊
Okay.
好
That's hot.
真是热呀
Good thing she takes my advice.
真听话
I'll put these in the closet for her.
给她放到屋里柜子了
That's better.
舒坦
So cute.
好可爱呀
Little Watermelon.
小西瓜
Look, look, look.
看看看
Over here.
看这边
Look,
看看
Mommy's here to see you.
来啦 妈妈来看了
Mommy's here.
妈妈来看你了
Time for a little massage.
我们开始做抚触喽
How do we do it?
怎么弄啊 阿姨
Well, follow my lead.
来 跟着一起弄啊
Okay.
好嘞
I'll do it.
我来
Yes, see? Like this.
对 您看这样 这样
Like this, gently rub upwards.
你这样 往上揉
Got it.
好嘞
I need a bit more massage oil.
多来点油
Here.
来
My hands are a bit rough.
我这粗手
Nice and gentle.
慢一点 轻一点啊
One, two, three.
一二三
Have a try.
让爸爸试试了啊
Be gentle.
轻轻的
That's it.
对对对
Slower, please.
再慢一点
Yes, a bit higher.
对 再往上一点
Perfect.
对
Feels so good, right, baby?
舒服舒服啊
How many times a day should we do this?
这每天要做几次啊
Once after
每天洗完澡
every bath.
就可以做一次
After every bath?
每次洗完澡
It helps newborns sleep better.
然后对那个睡眠特别好
Look how quickly your daddy's learning!
你看爸爸学得多快呀
You're such a good dad.
你真是个好爸爸
Thanks.
是
Let's start with the armpits, then go upwards.
先这个胳肢窝 往上
The armpits.
胳肢窝
Yeah, both sides.
一起做
Then upwards.
往上
Now gently move the baby's little arms.
然后这个小胳膊这么转
Move them?
要转是吗
Yes, like this.
转 对
That's right.
转一下 对
Gently, gently.
轻一点 轻一点
Well done.
对对对
This is my second child.
这是我们家老二了呀
Second one?
老二啦
That explains why
怪不得呢
you're such a pro.
你这学得这么快 是吧
See? Isn't Daddy doing a great job?
你看 爸爸好不好啊
Isn't he learning
爸爸是不是
really fast?
学得特别快呀
Now, let's rub the baby's tummy.
再揉揉肚肚啊
A gentle tummy rub.
揉肚肚
That's impressive.
可以啊
Congratulations!
恭喜啊
Thank you.
谢谢
It's only been a few months,
这才几个月呀
and you're like a whole new person!
脱胎换骨了吗
I'm thinking of switching careers.
我准备改行了
Back to investment banks?
回投行
Yeah, I like doing this kind of job.
我对投行还是有感情的
And after these past few months,
我通过这几个月的锻炼
I've gained some insight
我对现在的职场
into the job market.
还算是有些了解
I think I'm ready to jump back in.
我觉得我有能力回去
Have you sent out any resumes?
投简历了吗
Yeah, to a few
投了几家
solid firms in finance.
金融行业内不错的公司
I'm in the first round of interviews now.
正在进行第一轮面试
Need me to bring Rachel in
要不要我再把瑞秋
for help?
叫下来
No, thanks.
不用
I've got this.
我现在应付得了
Great.
真棒
Can't wait to hear the good news.
期待你的好消息
Thanks.
好啊
How about you?
你怎么样啊
You're pregnant
你身上怀着孕
and still working.
工作起来
How are you holding up?
身体吃得消吗
Physically, I'm okay.
身体还可以
But mentally...
就是这心理吧
Here is the thing.
这么说吧
You know,
你知道对于一个
when you're a 40-year-old woman
四十岁的
in the workplace,
职场孕妇来说哈
and suddenly everyone's
大家对你的关注
more focused on your belly
突然从工作
than your work,
转到了肚子的时候
it makes me feel odd,
还是让我有点
and I'm still not getting used to it.
不太适应的
But at the same time,
但是这份心理呢
it's complicated.
又很矛盾
Because
因为
I can't let myself get too tired,
我既不能让自己太累
but I also don't want others thinking
也不能让人家觉得我
I'm slacking off.
什么都干不了
Finding that balance
这个分寸啊
is kinda tricky.
有点难拿捏的
Yeah.
是
Well,
我吧
when I was pregnant,
怀孕的时候
I already left work.
已经离开职场了
So I can't fully relate to
你这种心理吧 我还
how you're feeling.
真不了解
But I bet you've got everything under control.
你肯定都安排好了吧
I know you too well.
我还不了解你
Stop playing the sympathy card with me.
你别在我面前装可怜了
Alright,
行了
you got me.
失败了
I've made some arrangements,
安排肯定是安排了
but I have to see how things go.
但是也得走一步看一步
As long as the boss
只要老板
doesn't give me a hard time,
不借题发挥的话
I should be able to manage.
就能苟住一切
Well, you must
什么苟住
hang in there.
挺住
That's not easy
人到中年
at our age.
哪儿那么容易挺啊
The resilience we had when we were young,
年轻那会儿的坚韧拼搏
there's not much
活到这岁数的时候
left of it now.
没剩下啥了好吗
If it's so tough,
那既然这么憋屈
why don't you just quit?
辞职呗
How could I?
那怎么能行呢
That's not an option.
那不就完了吗
You're trying to trick me?
你套路我
It's fine to vent out
这负面情绪吧
negative feelings sometimes,
可以发泄发泄
but we still
但是我们呢
need to stay hopeful
要对未来
about the future.
还是抱有希望的
Keep going,
加油
I believe in you.
我看好你哦
You're so cheeky.
淘气
Mr. Jia,
贾先生
you have strong
您的抗压能力
resilience and
和适应能力
adaptability.
都挺强的
You've been optimistic about having a second child,
面对二胎也积极乐观
without the anxiety or stress
没有新手爸爸的那种
that first-time fathers often experience.
种焦虑和压抑
Doctor,
医生
I'm not anxious
我一点都不焦虑
or depressed at all.
一点都不压抑
In fact, I'm thrilled!
我高兴还来不及呢
Honestly, I didn't even
其实我做不做这个测试
need this test.
都无所谓
I only came
我主要是我太太
because my wife
不愿意来做
didn't want to.
所以我就来了
Your wife...
您太太
From what I've observed recently,
根据我最近的观察
I think she's
我认为
showing signs of postpartum depression.
她是典型的产后抑郁
Depression?
抑郁
What should I do?
那该怎么办呀
Don't worry too much.
您也不用过分担心
Clinically,
临床上
around 40% of women
有百分之四十的女性
experience
多多少少
different levels of
都会有不同程度的
postpartum depression.
产后抑郁
During this time,
这段时期呢
you should spend more time with her
您应该多陪伴
and be as understanding as possible.
多体谅您的太太
After childbirth,
她刚刚生产完
her hormone levels
体内的激素水平
drop drastically,
是急剧下降
and this can cause
所以会造成
both physical and emotional
对身体和心理的
challenges.
双重不适
Doctor,
医生
as a professional,
您是心理医生
you understand people's minds
那比我们老百姓懂得多
better than
一定能拿捏住
most of us.
我们老百姓的心理
Given my wife's situation,
那我老婆这个
how can I help her?
我怎么才能帮到她啊
You'll need to be patient
只能慢慢地做工作
and try to get her to open up.
让她敞开心扉
But it's also important that
但是这事呢
you, as her husband,
我们也需要您作为家属
provide her with support and security.
给她提供依靠和支持
As long as Xin is happy,
只要心心高兴
I'll do whatever it takes.
我怎么样都行
Doctor,
医生
I've been feeling overwhelmingly
我这一会儿高兴
excited and joyful.
一会儿激动的
Is there something wrong
我是不是也有点
with me too?
病了
Look,
你说说人家
the meals at the postpartum center
月子中心的营养餐
are really nutritious,
这不是很好的吗
but she finds them tasteless.
不吃
She keeps asking for other things,
非要买这个 买那个
but then doesn't eat those either.
这买来了也不吃啊
Then she insists on eating
非要吃你丈母娘
only what her mom makes.
自己做的
Now that it's here,
这不是送来了吗
she still won't touch it.
这怎么还不吃啊
Mom, it's okay.
妈 没事
I just don't know what she really wants to eat.
也不知道她想吃啥
Alright, alright, it won't go to waste.
行了行了 浪费不了
Please lower your voice.
您小点声啊
Just take it home for you and the driver.
拿回家您跟司机吃
It's very nutritious.
营养丰富
Haowen, let me tell you something,
浩文 我可提醒你啊
you can't
你可不能
keep spoiling Xin like this.
再这么惯着心心了
Don't you see
你看她对你
the way she treats you?
那什么态度啊
I can't stand it.
我都看不下去
Mom, I'm not spoiling her.
妈 我没惯她
It's postpartum depression.
这不产后抑郁症吗
The doctor said,
医生都说了
she needs our support now
这个时候心心
more than ever.
最需要家人的陪伴
We need to help her through this together.
共渡难关
What?
什么呀
Postpartum depression?
还产后抑郁症
Is that even a thing?
说得跟真的似的
I've been through this.
那我一个过来人
What don't I know?
我什么不知道啊
She's just using
她这次就是想
this postpartum thing
趁着坐月子
as an excuse to boss you around.
好好地治治你
No, Mom.
没有 妈
Xin has never been like this.
我们家心以前不这样
She's always been so good to me.
对我好着呢
Why didn't she act like this
她生第一个孩子的时候
after having your first child?
怎么不这样啊
That was when she was younger.
那时候不是年轻吗
And back then,
那会儿工作又忙
I was busy with work.
咱也没时间陪她
And this time,
再说这次
it was a C-section.
这不剖腹产嘛
She has a big scar on her belly.
还有一大疤呢
It hasn't healed well,
这不没养好
so of course, she's feeling upset.
心情肯定不好嘛
Haowen, let me tell you,
浩文啊 我告诉你啊
if you let her
你这次要是
have her way this time,
被她拿捏住了
you'll regret it later.
以后有你受的
You'll end up making money
你又要赚钱养家
and taking care of her too.
又得伺候她
Why should you have to do it all?
她凭什么呀
Mom, that's such old thinking.
妈 您都啥年代
When we first got married,
这两口子过日子
I didn't have a penny
当年您儿子
to my name,
一文不名的时候
and she stuck with me
人可是跟着我
through it all.
受过苦的啊
Besides,
再说了
she's given you a grandson
今天给您又生一个
and a granddaughter.
大孙子孙女的
You should be happy about it.
您多开心 偷着乐吧
Mom, besides you,
我跟你说 妈
there's no other woman
这世界上除了您
in this world
没有第二个女人
who treats me as well as she does.
像她对我那么好
I know.
我知道
I'm just worried about you.
我这不是心疼你吗
You have
你说你
been here with her
陪着她
for almost a month now.
坐月子也快一个月了吧
Aren't you going back to work?
你不上班了
Guess why I chose to run my own company.
那我为什么当老板
That's because
当老板
I can go to the office when I want to
就是为了想来就来
and skip it when I don't.
不想来就不来
I can work when I feel like it
想上就上
and take off when I don't.
不想上就不上
But won't that affect your company?
那不耽误挣钱哪
You've got so many employees depending on you.
你公司还有这么多人
Aren't you usually very busy?
你平时不挺忙的吗你
Mom,
妈
that's what employees are for,
这么多人养着是干吗的
to handle the business for me.
就是给老板扛事的
Mom, here.
妈 来来来
This is for you.
这个是给您的哎
What's this?
什么呀
You're my mom.
您可是我老娘
I know exactly what you like.
我最知道您爱什么
Go ahead, open it.
看看哎
A gold bracelet?
大金子
Take it, Mom.
拿着啊 妈
What's this for?
你给我这干吗呀
To help you
那不就是为了让您
cool off a little.
消消气嘛 时刻的
So you are doing this for your wife?
还是为你媳妇
Mom,
妈
please remember,
您要记着
you're here to
您这次来是干吗的
help take care of Xin
伺候月子的
and your grandchildren,
而且照顾孙子跟孙女的
not to argue with your daughter-in-law.
不是来跟儿媳妇打架的
I know.
我知道
But did you see how she treats me?
可你看她对我那态度
I'm still her elder, after all.
我好歹也是个长辈吧
Mom,
妈
she is dealing with depression.
这不有抑郁症
She's not in a good mood.
心情不好吗
It's not just you.
她不是光对您
She's even worse with her own parents.
她对她爸她妈更厉害
I've seen it firsthand.
那我可真看见了
I get it, I do,
这道理我知道
but I still feel
可是我这心里
so annoyed.
就是窝囊啊
Mom, isn't that what the bracelet is for?
妈 这不是窝囊费吗
I've already paid for that.
这窝囊费我不都付了吗
Please be more patient.
这叫窝囊费的钱
I know,
我知道
when she's discharged,
等她出院的时候
I'll get you an even bigger one.
我给您买一个更大的啊
It would be so heavy
那大镯子您戴上
that you wouldn't be able
都坠得慌
to lift your hand.
手都抬不起来
You brat,
臭小子
always know how to make me smile.
就会哄人
Tell me.
说吧
Tell you what?
说什么呀
How to take care of your dad.
怎么照顾你爸呀
And how to manage the housework.
家里活怎么干哪
Your Dad's getting out of the hospital in a few days.
你爸没两天就出院了
Do I look like someone
你觉得我在家
who's cut out for housework?
像是个干活的人
I forgot.
忘了
That's one thing you got from me,
你就这点随我
marrying a good husband.
找了个好老公
So, you're asking the wrong person.
所以你找错人了
You should be asking Li Lin.
这事你应该找李临啊
Come on.
不是
How can I
我一丈母娘
ask my son-in-law
我怎么能跟姑爷
about this stuff?
问这些事啊
Didn't I already ask Lanxiang
我不是都把兰香
to come over and help?
给你弄过来了吗
That's not the same.
那能一样吗
I'm taking care of my husband.
你爸是兰香老头啊
Let me tell you,
我跟你说
looking after your dad is my job,
贴身照顾你爸这事
not even you or Xin can step in.
你和心心都不能插手
But I feel,
不过我觉得
over the years,
这些年
I've been so spoiled by your dad.
我真的被你爸养废了
I remember back when I lost my job,
想当年下岗的时候
I was only 40.
我才四十岁
You were 15 then,
那时候你十五
and Xin was eight.
心心八岁
It felt like my whole world was collapsing.
我就觉着天都塌了
Do you know how your dad got through that?
你知道你爸怎么撑的吗
Every morning, he got up early,
他每天一大早
made breakfast for the three of us,
给咱们娘儿仨做完早餐
and then took me out to run our fried chicken stall.
就带着我出去摆炸鸡摊
He wouldn't let me do a thing,
什么都不让我干
just collect the money.
就让我收钱
After we called it a day,
晚上收摊之后
he'd go to
他还跑到人家那个
a restaurant
司机饭店
and worked as a cook.
去给人颠勺
Back then, I felt like
那时候我就觉着
there was hope in life again.
我们家的天又撑起来了
To me,
在我心目中
your dad was my whole world.
你爸就是我的天
But now, that world has crumbled again.
可现在 天又塌了
So I think
我就觉着
I need to be brave this time.
我应该撑起来
It's a bit late, huh?
有点晚了哈
But maybe it's not too late.
是不还来得及
It's not too late.
来得及
You've got this, Mom.
我觉得你没问题 妈
You have my full support.
加油 我支持你
Really?
真的
You know what?
我跟你说
In the ward,
在病区
your dad's the one
你爸是
recovering the fastest.
恢复得最好的那个
He says,
他说
just thinking about the baby you're carrying
只要想到你肚里的孩子
and Xin's
还有心心
new born daughter
刚生的那小女儿
makes him feel hopeful.
他就觉得日子有盼头
I think once he's back home,
我觉着他回来之后
with me taking care of him,
有我贴身照顾
he'll get even better.
他指定能更好
With you looking after him,
你都贴身照顾了
he's bound to be just fine.
肯定没问题的
An,
安安
I really love talking with you.
我就特喜欢和你聊天
It feels like I've raised
我就觉着我
a grown son.
养了个大儿子
You not only make me proud,
不但给我长脸 你
you also give me strength.
还给我鼓劲
Why do I feel like I've
我怎么觉得我像
had another daughter?
多养了一闺女啊
Nonsense.
瞎说什么呀
I'm your mom.
又没大没小
Look at you.
你看你看 你看你那样
Come on, cheer up.
支棱起来
Good.
乖啊
Here.
来
Tasty, right?
好吃吧
Yeah, it's delicious.
好吃的
Then have some more.
好吃就多吃点
You're so considerate.
还是你对我好
Of course.
那必须的
If you like it,
你要是喜欢吃呢
just let me know anytime.
你就随时告诉我
I'm your best delivery guy.
我是你最好的外卖员
Try this.
尝尝这个
What is it?
怎么了
You done eating?
不吃了
Did Xu Meng'an send you?
许梦安让你来的吧
I knew it.
一猜就是
These flavors
就这几个口味
are all her favorites.
都是她自己爱吃的
Where is she?
她人呢
Why doesn't she come here herself?
她怎么自己不来啊
Would she dare?
她敢吗
What wouldn't she dare?
她有什么不敢的呀
She has even got guts
她主意多大呀
to make decisions for others.
谁的事她都能做主
No, this time it's different.
不 这次不一样
This is the first time I've seen her
我第一次见到你姐啊
look so pitiful,
那可怜兮兮
almost desperate,
低三下四的
even pleading with me to come and talk to you.
非得求我 来替她求情
I don't believe it.
才不信
It's true, really!
真的 真的
You should've seen her.
你是没见到她那样
She grabbed my hands,
紧握我的双手
tears in her eyes,
满含热泪
looked so pitiful,
可怜兮兮 贱不兮兮的
and almost knelt in front of me.
就差点跪我面前了
She said
她说她现在
she's so afraid of seeing you right now.
特别怕看到你
When she came to see you that day,
她那天来见你
you could see it in her eyes.
你看她那眼神
Literally.
那简直了
She was scared and nervous.
她心里发慌 发毛
I,
我
I should've recorded her then,
我当时应该把她录下来
so you could see it.
给你看
You'd have enjoyed it for sure.
你看了肯定开心
Just thinking about it now makes me laugh.
我现在想想就挺开心
Feels good, huh?
开心吧
So satisfying.
痛快
Exactly, satisfying.
对 痛快
As long as you're happy.
开心就好
Don't be fooled by
别看你姐
your sister's tough facade,
平时说一不二的
but actually,
其实
she's really scared.
她挺后怕的
The pressure is really getting to her.
心理压力特别大
When she pushed Haowen to sign,
她当时逼着浩文签字
she was just really desperate.
那也是挺着急的
If something happened to the baby,
那万一胎儿有事了
both you and the child
你跟孩子
would be in danger.
不就有危险了吗
I know, I really do.
其实道理我都懂
I just can't get past it.
我就是心里过不去
Yeah, I understand.
是 我知道
Xin, don't overthink it.
心心 先别想那么多了
Look at you now, you're doing great.
你看你现在不挺好的吗
You had a son and a daughter, and you're healthy.
一儿一女 母女平安
You're in the recovery period.
你现在是恢复期
Once you're fully healed,
等身体养好了 恢复了
you can have
让你姐
your sister
再给你
put on another show for you.
可怜兮兮地演一遍
Tell her to make it really pathetic this time.
要贱兮兮的
Right, right, really pathetic.
对对对 贱兮兮
It's hard to imagine
我姐还有这种时候呢
my sister acting like this.
没想到啊
She does care about you, though.
其实她挺心疼你的
If you like it, I'll have her make more for you.
喜欢吃我再让她给你做
She made this?
这是她做的
Oops, slipped.
说漏嘴了
I knew it.
我说嘛
All these are
做来做去
her favorite flavors.
都是她自己喜欢的口味
She spent all morning on it.
做了一上午呢
This is her best effort?
她就这个水平
It's pretty bad.
菜得很
Wanna try it?
你尝尝
I already did.
我尝过了
This one doesn't look great.
这个太丑了
But it tastes alright.
挺好吃的
She knows
她好歹
something about fashion design.
带我去那个服装设计的
Where's her sense of aesthetics?
你说这审美
Seriously.
什么呀
I'll talk to her later.
回头我说说她
So you're not mad anymore?
不生气了
That depends.
看她表现
Show me how she begged you.
怎么跟我求情
Give me that
你再给我学学那个表情
pathetic look.
贱不兮兮的样子
Please, Wanzhen, just go.
求你了 婉真 你去嘛
Why did you agree
你为什么这么快
so quickly?
答应下来
You should've let her try harder.
你让她多演一会儿
I couldn't take it anymore.
我看不下去了
Why are you still here
怎么还在这儿
working so hard by yourself?
自己吭哧吭哧地干活呢
Didn't you say you would
不是说好了
train the new hires and build teams?
搭班子带新人的吗
It's not too much trouble.
我就捎带手的事
If I left it to them,
你让他们弄至少
it'd take half a day,
还得半天的时间
while I can get it done
我这噼里啪啦的
in half an hour.
半个小时就完了
They say in our media industry,
都说咱们这传媒行业
women work like men,
女的当男的使
and men work like machines.
男的当机器使
But you,
您这可好
treat yourself like
直接拿自己
a workhorse machine.
当扛活的机器呢
Are you here to cheer me on?
那你是来给我加油的吗
Stop joking.
严肃点
Sit up straight.
坐好了
Head up, chest out.
抬头挺胸
Hold out your hand.
伸出手来
What for?
干吗呀
To receive the decree.
接旨
What decree?
什么呀
Take a look.
看看
An invitation?
邀请函
Top 10 Influential Women Awards?
十大影响力女性人物
I got this for you.
我给你争取到的
What is it?
是什么
An award ceremony, of course.
颁奖礼啊
When is it held?
什么时候啊
This Sunday.
周日
This Sunday?
周日啊
I can't make it.
周日不行
But I've got a client meeting on Sunday.
周日我约了客户了
I think I'll skip it.
就不去了吧
Why waste time on this flashy stuff?
与其弄这些虚头巴脑的
I'd rather get more business
还不如给公司
for the company.
多拉点活呢
Yeah, work needs to be done and done well,
活得干 而且得干好
reputation matters too.
但是名 咱也得要啊
If you're planning to step back,
你要退居二线
you need to keep your name out there.
就得多刷刷存在感
Make sure Mr. Zhang
得让老张
realizes
一直知道
your place in the industry.
你在业界的地位
Work is the obvious front,
工作是明修栈道
but this is also the battlefield.
这是暗度陈仓
When it's time for your comeback,
等有一天你杀回来
this will be your leverage.
这就是武器
You know how much effort it took
你知道我给你弄这奖项
to get you this award?
费了多大劲吗
Did you pull strings?
你黑幕了
Why would I need to?
你用得着吗
You have to go.
得去
I'll go.
去
Alright, everyone, raise your glasses.
来 大家把酒端起来
Congrats to Feifei for closing another deal!
恭喜菲菲 又开单了
Congrats! Cheers!
恭喜 恭喜
Thank you.
谢谢
As for the big invite event tomorrow,
明天 是邀请会啊
keep up the good work, everyone!
大家可要继续努力
Cheers!
来 干杯
You have to work hard.
干
We'll.
好嘞
Our department's wealthy lady
咱部门这个贵妇啊
really knows how to kill the vibe.
真是扫兴
But even without closing deals,
不过人家不开单呢
she still rides in luxury cars
也能坐豪车
and lives in fancy houses.
住好房子
We're not like her.
咱们可跟人家不一样
We have to hustle, got it?
咱们得努力 知道吗
Yes.
对
Alright, alright,
好了 好了
don't let her ruin our mood.
别让她影响咱们心情
Come on.
来
Let's drink!
干杯
Cheers! Cheers!
干杯 干杯 干杯
Guys, take a bite before it gets cold.
大家快吃 一会儿凉了
Hurry up, try some.
快快快 快吃
Okay.
好好好
Oh, right,
还有那个
Mr. Qian,
钱总
I need to toast to you personally.
我单独得敬您一下
Without your help,
没有您的帮助
I wouldn't have done so well.
我也没有这么好的业绩
Cheers, Feifei.
来 菲菲
Keep it that way.
继续加油
Thanks, Mr. Qian.
谢钱总
Okay, give me one.
可以 拿一个
Congrats to Meng'an,
恭喜梦安
for being nominated for a major award.
入围重量级奖项
Congrats, Ms. Xu.
恭喜许总监
This honor belongs not only Ms. Xu,
这是许总监的荣誉
but also our entire company.
也是我们新苗的骄傲
Everyone, let's give her a big hand!
大家 热烈鼓掌
Great!
好
Applause!
鼓掌
Come in.
进
Mr. Qian.
钱总
Yes?
什么事
When am I getting
我的那一半提成
my share of the commission?
什么时候给我啊
Chen Wanzhen,
陈婉真
you planning to quit?
你是想离职是吧
Yes, I am,
我是想离职啊
But
但是
I'm not leaving
我的提成没有拿完
until I get my full commission.
我是不会走的
Chen Wanzhen, you're really something.
陈婉真 你可以啊
You schemed your way
处心积虑地
into our sales department,
转到我们销售部
worked for a few months, and now you want to leave,
干了没几个月就想走
with full commission?
而且想拿走全部
Are you being
你是不是
a housewife for so long
当家庭主妇当久了
that you think
你以为全世界
the world revolves around you?
都得围着你转
Is that it?
是吧
Mr. Qian,
钱总
take a look at this report.
你看看这份报告
Chen Wanzhen,
陈婉真
where did you get these documents?
你这些资料从哪儿来的
This is internal information.
这些都是内部资料
You know I could charge you with theft
我告你个监守自盗
and put you in jail, right?
让你蹲大牢 你信不信
Mr. Qian,
钱总
this is all publicly available data
这都是各个金融机构
from various financial institutions,
公开的财务数据
including our company's figures,
包括我们公司的数据
in the annual reports.
也是公开的年报
I simply
我只是做了一个
compiled and analyzed them.
汇总分析
And finally I drew my own conclusions.
得出了我的结论
These are just my personal opinions.
仅代表我个人的观点
As for my resignation letter
我的辞职报告呢
and commission request,
和销售提成的申领单
I've already submitted them to headquarters.
已经向公司总部提交了
Please approve them at your earliest convenience.
请您尽快批复我
Thank you, Mr. Qian,
谢谢钱总
for your help during this time.
这段时间承蒙你照顾我
You can take a close look
这份报告
at this report if you like.
你仔细看一看
Congratulations, Ms. Xu!
恭喜啊 许总监
Thanks.
辛苦啊 谢谢啊
Get in there.
给我进去
What are you doing?
你这是要干吗呀
Promoting.
宣传哪
Didn't you put up some in the restroom?
厕所没贴两张吗
Thanks for the reminder.
提醒我了
I'll get it done
马上搞两张
right away.
贴卫生间去
Come on,
大姐
what kind of promotion is this?
你这哪儿是宣传啊
That's a flattery trap, you know?
你这是捧杀 知道吗
Aren't you working in new media?
还搞新媒体内容的
Don't you know the art of marketing?
不知道传播的奥义啊
I don't need you
业务的事情
to school me on business.
就不用你教我了吧
Not a chance.
那不行
You might forget it.
万一你忘了呢
So I need to remind you.
还是得教教你
You need to anchor
你现在得给受众群
the audience's minds.
一个心理锚点
Anchor who?
我给谁锚点啊
Our company.
公司啊
Right now,
现在的你
you're the anchor for the company's image.
就是公司的心理锚点
Can we just drop this?
咱能不锚点了吗
You're making this such a big deal of it,
你说你搞这么大的阵仗
but is anyone benefiting?
有受益人吗
You are.
你呀
How's this possible?
这怎么可能呢
Dear,
我的姐姐
I'm pregnant now,
我现在怀孕了
I need to work hard and keep a low profile.
要高调做事 低调做人
I wish
我这恨不得
I could just
在大家
have this baby
都没反应过来的时候
before anyone notices,
就生完了孩子
take the maternity leave,
休完了产假
and slip back into work.
鸟不悄地回来了
But if you make me the anchor,
你现在把我搞成锚点
everyone will be watching me!
全公司的人都瞄着我
How am I supposed to take time off?
我还怎么休产假
Hiding won't help.
装鸵鸟是没有用的
How come?
怎么会没用呢
Besides,
况且我现在
it's just a nomination.
也就是个提名
I haven't actually won it yet.
没说得奖
And what if I don't win?
那万一不得奖呢
We'll just pretend nothing ever happens?
集体演尴尬吗
What I'm doing here
我做这些跟你得不得奖
has nothing to do with you winning or not.
没有一点关系哦
I'm doing all this
我做这些
just because you're pregnant.
恰恰因为你怀了孕呀
Come with me.
跟我过来
Look.
看
Xu Meng'an,
许梦安
Chief Content Officer of Xinmiao Media.
新苗公司首席内容官
Once honored,
曾获荣誉
Top 10 Leaders
春江市
in Chunjiang City's Integrated Media.
融媒体十大领军人物
in Chunjiang City's Online Audio-Visual Industry.
网络视听行业杰出人才
Anyone who looks at this poster
每个人过来一看这海报
will see those lines.
都能看到这两行字呀
I want to make sure
我就是要
that Mr. Zhang and everyone at the company
让张总和公司所有人
gets the message
都能读到
behind these lines,
这两行字的潜台词
that you, Xu Meng'an, are truly exceptional.
你许梦安真的很能干呀
When it comes to real talent,
真正的实力面前
we don't need to
我们用不着
play games
搞那些策略呀
or tricks.
技巧呀
Don't you want to
你不是想降低
lower your profile?
你的关注度吗
Well,
你看
nobody is focused on your pregnancy now.
谁还关注你的肚子
I want everyone in this company
我就是要让公司所有人
to always live in
都永远活在
your shadow.
你的阴影之下
Why don't you just make sure
你干脆让我永远活在
I live in their minds forever?
他们心里算了
Then I have to put a frame around it.
那我还得搞个框
Thanks.
谢谢啊
But how about something more practical?
来点实际的
How about a boyfriend?
发你个男朋友
I'd love that.
这个可以有